{"tossups": [{"question": "Donald Trump recently claimed that this organization had opened a hotel and that he was \u201cin competition with them.\u201d This group was driven out of Tikrit after massacring unarmed Air Force cadets at Camp Speicher. The Bataclan was targeted by this group in a November 2015 attack in Paris. For ten points, name this extremist Islamic terrorist group that arose from an offshoot of Al-Qaeda and which controls territory in Iraq and Syria.", "answer": "<b> Islamic State</b> of Iraq and Syria (or<b> Islamic State</b> of Iraq and the Levant; accept<b> ISIS</b>, <b>ISIL</b>, or<b> IS</b>; accept<b> Daesh</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man led the fleet that claimed Cayo Hueso, later known as Key West. He threatened gunboat diplomacy at Uraga with a fleet of four gunboats; in ensuing discussion, he broke the isolationist policy of sakoku. The Convention of Kanagawa was signed by, for ten points, what American commodore who opened trade with Japan?", "answer": "<b> M</b>atthew<b> Perry</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Carlo Maderno expanded the nave of a building in this city. A fountain in this city includes a dove representing the Pamphili family atop an Egyptian obelisk that overlooks the fountain\u2019s depiction of four rivers. An amphitheatre in this city was built during the Flavian dynasty near the site of chariot racing at the Circus Maximus. For ten points, name the city that contains St. Peter\u2019s Basilica and the Colosseum.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b> (prompt on Vatican City)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This writer compared journalists with prostitutes in his expose<em> The Brass Check</em>. In another book by this man, the protagonist\u2019s wife Ona is raped by Phil Connor, and its Lithuanian protagonist attending a Socialist rally; that book caused this author to claim \u201cI aimed for the public\u2019s heart, and by accident hit it in the stomach.\u201d Jurgis Rudkus works in an unsanitary meatpacking plant in, for ten points, what muckracking author\u2019s<em> The Jungle</em>?", "answer": "Upton<b> Sinclair</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "To extend its shoreline, this city built the Palm Jumeirah, just south of a set of hundreds of small artificial islands in the shape of the world. A three-lobed skyscraper in this city uses spiralling setbacks along its 160 floors. For ten points, name this most populous city in the United Arab Emirates, where oil revenue has spurred urban construction like the Burj Khalifa.", "answer": "<b> Dubai</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In this battle, Major Sylvain-Raynal managed to defend Fort Vaux for over a week, but the lightly defended Fort Douaumont [DOO-oh-MOHN] was captured without a fight. General Nivelle issued the order \u201cthey shall not pass\u201d during this battle, and General Falkenhyn sought to \u201cbleed France white\u201din this battle. For ten points, name this extremely bloody 9-month-long battle during World War I at a French fortress town.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Verdun</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Three of this body\u2019s first five acts dealt with Soviet occupation of Iran. Its operation is controversial, as the victorious Allied countries in World War II hold permanent member status and veto power, unlike in the General Assembly where non-binding resolutions are voted on. For ten points, name this 15-member body that orders sanctions and peacekeeping operations for the United Nations.", "answer": "United Nations<b> Security Council</b> (do not prompt on United Nations)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These entities were controlled through \u201cingenuity\u201d among other things, utilizing both a mahout and a howdah. Among the most famous use of this weapon was at the Battle of the Hydaspes River by King Porus against Alexander the Great. Hannibal baffled the Romans by crossing the Alps with them. For ten points, name this animal, akin to an ancient tank, which is now hunted for its ivory tusks.", "answer": "<b> elephant</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this South American culture which built cities like Cuzco and Machu Picchu.", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John Mitchel was sent to Bermuda as punishment for his writings about this event. During this event, people called \u201csoupers\u201d converted to Protestantism in return for aid. The cottier system worsened this event, in which the affected area received shipments of maize known as \u201cPeel\u2019s brimstone\u201d and remained a net food exporter to Britain. For ten points, over a million people starved in what event in which the staple crop of an island west of Britain was ruined by blight?", "answer": "<b> Irish Potato Famine</b> [or<b> Great Famine</b>, or<b> Great Hunger</b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Following the acceptance of this theory, Koch\u2019s Postulates were developed. Girolamo Fracastoro was the first to propose this theory, which Francesco Redi supported by observing 3 jars of meatloaf and eggs over time. The discrediting of spontaneous generation finally led to the widespread acceptance of this theory. For ten points, Galen\u2019s miasma theory was replaced by what theory that diseases are caused by microscopic organisms like viruses and bacteria?", "answer": "<b> germ</b> theory of disease", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "This person\u2019s childhood friend, the Princess de Lamballe, was murdered in the September Massacres. The Carnation Plot attempted to save this monarch, a suspected lover of Axel Fersin. This monarch was wrongly blamed in the Diamond Necklace affair and was derisively called \u201cthe Austrian\u201d. For ten points, name this Queen of France, who may have said \u201clet them eat cake\u201d and was guillotined after her husband Louis XVI.", "answer": "<b> Marie Antoinette</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to one battle, this man had a vision of enemy soldiers \u201cfalling like grasshoppers.\u201d After a brief exile in Canada, this leader surrendered and was held at Standing Rock, where he was later killed in a botched arrest attempt. For ten points, name this chief who toured with Buffalo Bill\u2019s Wild West well after leading the Lakota Sioux to victory over American forces at the Battle of Little Bighorn.", "answer": "<b> Sitting Bull</b> (or Thathanka<b> Iyotake</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In August 2015, one of these items was returned to NPR legal correspondent Nina Totenberg and her family 35 years after it was stolen from her father. In 2014, one of these objects named \u201cLipinski\u201d was stolen in Milwaukee after a performance of Olivier (+) </b> <b>Messiaen\u2019s</b><em><b> Quartet for the End of Time</b></em><b>. Wood density and varnish quality have been proposed as explanations for the (*) </b> brilliant sound of these instruments, which are roughly 300 years old. For ten points, name these instruments, reputed to be the finest-crafted violins in the world.", "answer": "<b> Stradivari</b>us violin (accept more general descriptions like<b> Stradivari</b>us instrument; prompt on violin; prompt on \u201cStrad;\u201d do not accept mentions of violas, cellos, etc.)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This man described his feud with Jimmy Hoffa in the book</b><em><b> The Enemy Within</b></em><b>. He sent troops to the University of Mississippi to protect James Meredith while serving as (+) Attorney General. He recalled Aeschylus in a speech at Indianapolis after the assassination of Martin Luther King, but was (*) </b> assassinated himself right after winning the 1968 California Democratic Presidential primary by Sirhan Sirhan. For ten points, name this younger brother of John F. Kennedy.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert Francis<b> Kennedy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Some structures along this body of water served as shelters for refugees from the Bar Kokhba Revolt. The first known copy of The Community Rule was found here, along with</b> <b>copies of known texts produced by the (+)</b> <b>Essenes. A famous discovery made near this</b> <b>body of water centered on several (*)</b> caves near Qumran. For ten points, name this body of water near which a large collection of Hebrew writings was found in the 1940s and 1950s, this place\u2019s namesake\u201cScrolls\u201d.", "answer": "<b> Dead Sea</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Duc de Longueville represented the French during the negotiations of this treaty. Despite this treaty, Spain and France did not cease hostilities until the Treaty of the (+) Pyrenees, and Sweden annexed Bremen after the signature of this treaty. It affirmed the independence of Switzerland and the Netherlands, and it extended the (*)</b> Peace of Augsburg by allowing Calvinism to be a German state\u2019s official religion. For ten points, name this peace treaty that ended the Thirty Years War.", "answer": "Peace of<b> Westphalia</b> or Treaty of<b> Westphalia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>As chair of the Foreign Relations committee, this man opposed the annexation of Santo</b> <b>Domingo. In a 112-page speech, he labeled Stephen Douglas the (+)</b> <b>Sancho Panza of</b> <b>slavery and Andrew Butler its Don Quixote; two days after delivering that speech, the (*)</b>\u201cCrime Against Kansas,\u201d he was attacked. For ten points, name this Radical Republican who was caned on the Senate floor by Preston Brooks.", "answer": "Charles<b> Sumner</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This President faced a war that was sparked by the Caroline Affair, and he was</b> <b>criticized by Charles Ogle in the Gold Spoon Oration. The Free Soil Party picked this</b> <b>man as their Presidential nominee in the election of (+) 1848, but his presidency was</b> <b>plagued by an economic downturn caused by his predecessor\u2019s (*)</b> Specie Circular Act. For ten points, name this President who succeeded Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "Martin Van<b> Buren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}